<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An impeachment of high treason exhibited in Parliament, against James, Lord Strange, son and heire apparant of William, Earle of Derby, by the Commons assembled in Parliament, in the name of themselves, and all the Commons of England. VVith an order of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, for the apprehending of the said Lord, to be published in all churches, and chappels, markets and townes, in the county of Lancaster and Chester. 16 September, 1642. Ordered by the Lords in Parliament assembled, that this impeachment, with the order, shall be forthwith printed and published. John Browne Cler. Parliament.</title>
            <author>Derby, James Stanley, Earl of, 1607-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2587B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E117_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871550</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871550</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E117[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An impeachment of high treason exhibited in Parliament, against James, Lord Strange, son and heire apparant of William, Earle of Derby, by the Commons assembled in Parliament, in the name of themselves, and all the Commons of England. VVith an order of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, for the apprehending of the said Lord, to be published in all churches, and chappels, markets and townes, in the county of Lancaster and Chester. 16 September, 1642. Ordered by the Lords in Parliament assembled, that this impeachment, with the order, shall be forthwith printed and published. John Browne Cler. Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Derby, James Stanley, Earl of, 1607-1651.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Septemb. 17. London Printed for John Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Derby, James Stanley, --  Earl of, 1607-1651.</term>
               <term>Impeachments --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156077:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:156077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <p>AN IMPEACHMENT OF HIGH TREASON Exhibited in PARLIAMENT, Againſt James, LORD STRANGE, Son and Heire apparant of <hi>William,</hi> Earle of <hi>Derby,</hi> by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, in the name of themſelves, and all the Commons of England.</p>
            <p>VVith an Order of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, for the apprehending of the ſaid Lord, to be publiſhed in all Churches, and Chappels, Markets and Townes, in the County of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> and <hi>Cheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>16 September, 1642.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Ordered by the Lords in Parliament Aſſembled, that this Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment, with the Order, ſhall be forthwith Printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>John Browne Cler. Parliament.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Septemb.</hi> 17. London Printed for John Wright, 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_impeachment">
            <pb facs="tcp:156077:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:156077:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
            <head>THE IMPEACHMENT OF <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> Son and Heire apparant of <hi>William</hi> Earle of <hi>Derby,</hi> by the Commons Aſſembled in Parliament, in the name of themſelves and all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> of High TRASON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the ſaid <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> to the intent and purpoſe to ſubvert the Fundamentall Lawes and Government of this Kingdome of England, and the Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and the very being of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and to ſet ſedition betwixt the King and his people; did upon the 15 day of July, in this preſent yeare of our Lord God, 1642 at
<pb facs="tcp:156077:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
               <pb facs="tcp:156077:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:156077:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->Mancheſter, in the County of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter, and at ſeverall other times and places, actually, maliciouſly, rebelliouſly, trayterouſly ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and called together, great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his Majeſties Subjects, and in ſight, perſwade and encourage them to take up armes and leavie war againſt the King, Parliament, and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>That the ſaid <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> in further proſecution of his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid wicked, trayterous, and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious purpoſes, did upon the ſaid 15 day of July, at Mancheſter afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and at ſeverall other times and places, actually, maliciouſly, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſly, and trayterouſly, raiſe great forces of men and horſe, and leavie war againſt the King, Parliament, and Kingdome, and in further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution
<pb facs="tcp:156077:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->of the aforeſaid wicked, trayterous, and malicious purpoſes, the ſaid ſame Lord <hi>Strange</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe other perſons, whom he had drawn into his party and faction, did alſo upon the ſaid 15 day of Iuly, at Mancheſter aforeſaid, maliciouſly, and trayterouſly, with force and armes, and in a hoſtile and warlike manner, kill, murder, and deſtroy, <hi>Richard Parcivall,</hi> of Kirkman-ſhalme, in the ſaid County of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter, <hi>Lynen Webster,</hi> and did then and there, &amp; at ſeverall other times and places, in like hoſtile manner as aforeſaid, ſhoot, ſtab, hurt and wound diverſe other of his Majeſties good Subjects, contrary to the Lawes and peace of this Kingdom of England, and contrary to his Majeſties Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crowne and Dignity; and the
<pb facs="tcp:156077:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->ſaid <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Srange,</hi> hath ſet ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt the King and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp; now is in open &amp; actuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt the King, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Kingdome. For which matters and things, the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes, of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament Aſſembled, doe in the name of themſelves, and of all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of England, Impeach the ſaid <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Strange</hi> of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the ſaid Commons by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, ſaving to themſelves the liberty of exhibiting at any time hereafter, any other accuſation or Impeachment againſt the ſaid Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> and alſo of replying to the anſwers of the ſaid <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Strange</hi> ſhall make to the Premiſes, or any of them, or any Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:156077:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->or accuſation that ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by them, as the Cauſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to courſe and proceedings of Parliament, ſhall require; do pray that the ſaid <hi>James</hi> Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> may be put to anſwer all and every the Premiſes, that ſuch proceedings, examinations, tryalls, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may be upon them, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them, had, and uſed, as ſhall bee agreeable to Law and Juſtice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order_of_execution">
            <pb facs="tcp:156077:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Veneris 16 Septembris 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas the Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> having continued a long time, and ſtill remaining in actuall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt his Majeſty, and Parliament, is for the ſame Impeached of high Treaſon by the Houſe of Commons, in the name of themſelves, and al the Commons of England. It is therefore Ordered by the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that publication thereof bee made in all Churches and Chappels, by the Curats and Church-Wardens thereof, and in all Markets and Townes, by the Conſtables and Officers of the Townes within the Counties of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>Cheſter,</hi> to the end that all his Maieſties loving Subiects may have notice thetof, leſt they being deceived by the ſpecious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made by the Lord <hi>Strange,</hi> ſhould aſſiſt him with men, money, munition, or any other Proviſion, and ſo make themſelves guilty of the like Treaſon and Rebellion, and all Sheriffs, and other his Maieſties ſubiects are hereby required to doe their beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour for the apprehenſion of the ſaid Lord, and the bringing him up to the Parliament, thereto receive condigne Puniſhment according to his demerits.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
